<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>CTO with CEO flavour</title><link href="https://alexmorozov.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://alexmorozov.github.io/feeds/tag-admin.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://alexmorozov.github.io/</id><updated>2015-11-03T10:20:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>When you shouldn’t use the Django admin</title><link href="https://alexmorozov.github.io/when-you-shouldnt-use-the-django-admin.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-03T10:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alex Morozov</name></author><id>tag:alexmorozov.github.io,2015-11-03:when-you-shouldnt-use-the-django-admin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In case you&amp;#8217;ve thought I detest &lt;code&gt;django.contrib.admin&lt;/code&gt; &amp;#8212; by no means.
Actually it&amp;#8217;s one of the Django&amp;#8217;s greatest features, I really love it. In most&amp;nbsp;cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a real life story. We&amp;#8217;ve had to quickly put up the first version of an
intranet claim tracking system, and one of our developers was just crazy about
the Django admin&amp;#8230; So why not, we&amp;#8217;ve got along with the stock interface as the
primary one for our&amp;nbsp;users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 years after that, I know for sure: I&amp;#8217;m the person who knows all the drawbacks
of such decision. And I want to share them with&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s my top 6 list of&amp;nbsp;problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stock templates&amp;nbsp;updates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The worst thing is often they pass through the testing sieve. Tests pass,
layout is broken, users complain. Upcoming 1.9 version introduces new flat
design and I&amp;#8217;m just afraid to&amp;nbsp;upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Unstable javascript &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the regular Django APIs, javascript ones are not guaranteed to be
stable. In addition, they are not so customizable - for example, you just can&amp;#8217;t
set a popup width without overriding the whole file.  On the other hand,
namespaced jQuery is really good. Most probably you won&amp;#8217;t have any versioning
problems between upgrades if you use additional jQuery for your own&amp;nbsp;purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Insufficient default&amp;nbsp;permissions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see a list of objects, Django admin gives you a convenient
&amp;#8216;changelist&amp;#8217; view. You can tweak in a lot of ways, which is cool, but there&amp;#8217;s a
major problem: to see a changelist, one has to have the &amp;#8216;change&amp;#8217; permission.
While it&amp;#8217;s perfectly normal for basic sites, more complex setups often need the
&amp;#8216;view&amp;#8217; permission, which allows to view a list of, say, tickets, while not
allowing to edit&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So one is on a fence between two options: either to lose the changelist
functionality, or to override the changelist view by copy-pasting 90% of the
code. Bad decisions, I must&amp;nbsp;say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No chance of using generic&amp;nbsp;CBVs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine some day we will see the Django admin based on the generic
class-based views. For now, if other parts of your site use CBVs for shared
behaviour, you must have some additional glue to add this behaviour to the
admin. You may recall context processors and middleware, but in my opinion
they are not as handy as a class&amp;nbsp;tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monolythic&amp;nbsp;implementation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;django.contrib.admin.options&lt;/code&gt; module is about 1 900 lines. I must say
the most of that code is very readable and straightforward, but dude, almost 2K
lines in one file! Reminds me of that Flask one-file web apps - you know, 10K
lines is not the limit. For those who interested, only &lt;code&gt;django.db.models&lt;/code&gt;
package have some larger&amp;nbsp;files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fieldsets handle only the basic&amp;nbsp;cases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the admin fieldsets, they&amp;#8217;re very handy when you work with relatively
simple models. If you want to organize some kind of tabs, collapsible
fieldsets, etc - you will have to code your own or to use custom&amp;nbsp;modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So&amp;nbsp;what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sure you get me right: the above is not about how bad the Django admin
is. It&amp;#8217;s about not putting too much expectations on the rather simple tool. So
dont repeat our mistakes. For me, here&amp;#8217;s the&amp;nbsp;formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider to stick with Django admin if two conditions are&amp;nbsp;met:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You expose the admin to the small group of experienced users (content&amp;nbsp;managers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your models, relations and workflow are simple&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="django"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="admin"></category></entry></feed>